Chapter 32. Slogy.
Already we are boldly launched upon the deep. But soon we shall be lost in its
unsured harborless immensities.
Air that come to pass, air the peekquad's wedi hull rolls side by side
with the barnacled hulls of the Leviathan. At the outset, it is but well
to attend to a matter almost indispensable to a thorough appreciative
understanding of the more special Leviathanic revelations and illusions of
all sorts which are to follow. It is some systematized exhibition of the
whale in his broad genera that I would now feain put before you. Yet it is no
easy task, the classification of the constituents of a chaos. Nothing less is
here essayed. Listen to what the best and latest authorities have laid down.
Quote, "No branch of zoologology is so much involved as that which is entitled
Slogy." End quote. Says Captain Scoresby, AD1820.
Quote, "It is not my intention, were it in my power, to enter into the inquiry
as to the true method of dividing the citation into groups and families. Utter
confusion exists among historians of this animal. End quote. Sperm whale says
surgeon beal ad 1839.
Quote unfitness to pursue our research in the unfathomable waters. End quote.
Quote impenetrable veil covering our knowledge of the sitatia. End quote.
Quote a field strewn with thorns. End quote. Quote, "All these incomplete
indications but serve to torture us naturalists." End quote. Thus speak of
the whale, the great Kouier and John Hunter, and lessen those lights of
zohology and anatomy. Nevertheless, though of real knowledge there be
little, yet of books there are a plenty.
And so in some small degree with cytology or the science of whales, many
are the men small and great, old and new, landsmen and seammen who have at
large or in little written of the whale.
Run over a few. The authors of the Bible, Aristotle, Ply, Aldra, Sir Thomas
Brown, Gzner, Ray, Lanaeus, Rond, Willoughby, Green, Art Teddy, Cibald,
Bisson, Martin, Lassipede, Bontter, Dear, Baron, Kovier, Frederick, Kovier,
John Hunter, Owen, Scoresby, Beal, Bennett, J. Ross Brown, the author of
Miriam Coffin, Olmstead, and the Reverend T. Chver. But to what ultimate
generalizing purpose all these have written, the above sited extracts will
show. Of the names in this list of whale authors, only those following Owen ever
saw living whales, and but one of them was a real professional harpooner and
whaleman, I mean, Captain Scoresby. On the separate subject of the Greenland or
Wright whale, he is the best existing authority. But Scoresby knew nothing and
says nothing of the great sperm whale, compared with which the Greenland whale
is almost unworthy mentioning. And here be it said that the Greenland whale is a
usurper upon the throne of the seas. He is not even by any means the largest of
the whales. Yet, owing to the long priority of his claims, and the profound
ignorance which until some 70 years back invested the then fabulous or utterly
unknown sperm whale, and which ignorance to this present day still reigns in all
but some few scientific retreats and whale ports, this usurppation has been
every way complete. reference to nearly all the Leviathanic illusions in the
great poets of past days will satisfy you that the Greenland whale without one
rival was to them the monarch of the seas. But the time has at last come for
a new proclamation. This is Chering Cross. Hear ye good people all. The
Greenland whale is deposed. The great sperm whale now reignth.
There are only two books in being which at all pretend to put the living sperm
whale before you and at the same time in the remotest degree succeed in the
attempt. Those books are bees and Bennetts both in their time surgeons to
English South Sea whale ships and both exact and reliable men. The original
matter touching the sperm whale to be found in their volumes is necessarily
small, but so far as it goes, it is of excellent quality, though mostly
confined to scientific description. As yet, however, the sperm whale,
scientific or poetic, lives not complete in any literature. Far above all other
hunted whales, his is an unwritten life.
Now the various species of whale need some sort of popular comprehensive classification,
if only an easy outline one for the present, hereafter to be filled in all
its departments by subsequent laborers, as no better man advances to take this
matter in hand, I here upon offer my own poor endeavors. I promise nothing
complete because any human thing supposed to be complete must for that
very reason infallibly be faulty. I shall not pretend to a minute anatomical
description of the various species or in this place at least to much of any
description. My object here is simply to project the draft of a systematization
of Sylogy. I am the architect not the builder.
But it is a ponderous task. No ordinary letter sorter in the post office is
equal to it. To grope down into the bottom of the sea after them, to have
one's hands among the unspeakable foundations, ribs, and very pelvis of
the world, this is a fearful thing. What am I that I should essay to hook the
nose of this Leviathan? The awful tauntings in Job might well appall me.
Will he, the Leviathan, make a covenant with thee? Behold, the hope of him is
vain. But I have swam through libraries and sailed through oceans. I have had to
do with whales with these visible hands.
I am an earnest, and I will try. There are some preliminaries to settle. First,
the uncertain unsettled condition of this science of cytology is in the very
vestibule attested by the fact that in some quarters it still remains a moot
point whether the whale be a fish. In his system of nature AD 1776,
Lanaeus declares, quote, I hereby separate the whales from the fish. End
quote. But I of my own knowledge know that down to the year 1850, sharks and
shad, alewives and herring against Lanaeus's express edict were still found
dividing the possession of the same seas with the Leviathan.
The grounds upon which Lanaeus would feain have banished the whales from the
waters. He states as follows, quote, on account of their warm blocular heart,
their lungs, their movable eyelids, their hollow ears, penum entrantum feminism,
end quote. And finally, ex leure juritoqu.
I submitted all this to my friends Simeon Macy and Charlie Coffan of
Nantucket, both messmates of mine in a certain voyage, and they united in the
opinion that the reasons set forth were altogether insufficient.
Charlie profainely hinted they were humbug.
Be it known that, waving all argument, I take the good old-fashioned ground that
the whale is a fish, and call upon holy Jonah to back me. this fundamental thing
settled. The next point is in what internal respect does the whale differ
from other fish? Above Lanaeus has given you those items, but in brief they are
these lungs and warm blood, whereas all other fish are lungless and cold-blooded.
Next, how shall we define the whale by his obvious externals, so as
conspicuously to label him for all time to come? To be short, then a whale is a
spouting fish with a horizontal tail.
There you have him. However contracted, that definition is the result of
expanded meditation. A walrus spouts much like a whale, but the walrus is not
a fish because he is amphibious. But the last term of the definition is still
more cogent as coupled with the first.
Almost anyone must have noticed that all the fish familiar to landsmen have not a
flat but a vertical or up and down tail.
Whereas among spouting fish the tail, though it may be similarly shaped,
invariably assumes a horizontal position.
By the above definition of what a whale is, I do by no means exclude from the
Leviathanic Brotherhood any sea creature hitherto identified with the whale by
the best informed Nantucketers, nor on the other hand link with it any
fish hitherto authoritatively regarded as alien. Hence all the smaller spouting
and horizontal tailed fish must be included in this grand plan of cytology.
Now then come the grand divisions of the entire whale host. Footnote. I am aware
that down to the present time the fishstyled lameins and dongs pigfish and
sowfish of the coffins of Nantucket are included by many naturalists among the
whales. But as these pigfish are a noisy, contemptable set, mostly lurking
in the mouths of rivers and feeding on wet hay, and especially as they do not
spout, I deny their credentials as whales, and have presented them with
their passports to quit the kingdom of Slogy. End of footnote.
First, according to magnitude, I divide the whales into three primary books
subdivisible into chapters, and these shall comprehend them all, both small
and large. One, the folio whale. Two, the octavo whale. Three, the duo decimo
whale. As the type of the folio, I present the sperm whale. of the octavo
the grampus of the duode decimo the porpus folios among these I here include the
following chapters one the sperm whale two the right whale three the finback
whale four the humpback whale five the razorback whale six the sulfur bottom whale
book one folio chapter one sperm whale.
This whale among the English of old, vaguely known as the trumpa whale and
the fissider whale and the anvilheaded whale is the present cashelo of the
French and the potsfish of the Germans and the macroephilis of the long words.
He is without doubt the largest inhabitant of the globe, the most
formidable of all whales to encounter, the most majestic in aspect, and lastly
by far the most valuable in commerce. He being the only creature from which that
valuable substance spermicetti is obtained. All his peculiarities will in
many other places be enlarged upon. It is chiefly with his name that I now have
to do. Philologically considered, it is absurd. some centuries ago, when the
sperm whale was almost wholly unknown in his own proper individuality, and when
his oil was only accidentally obtained from the stranded fish. In those days,
Spermaceti, it would seem, was popularly supposed to be derived from a creature
identical with the one then known in England as the Greenland or right whale.
It was the idea also that this same spermiceti was that quickening humor of
the Greenland whale which the first syllable of the word literally
expresses. In those times also spermaceti was exceedingly scarce, not
being used for light but only as an ointment and medicicament. It was only
to be had from the drugus as you nowadays by an ounce of rhubarb. When,
as Iopine, in the course of time, the true nature of Spermaceti became known,
its original name was still retained by the dealers, no doubt to enhance its
value by a notion so strangely significant of its scarcity, and so the
Appalachian must have at last come to be bestowed upon the whale from which this
spermicetti was really derived.
Book one, Folio, chapter 2, right whale.
In one respect, this is the most venerable of the Leviathans, being the
one first regularly hunted by man. It yields the article commonly known as
whale bone or baine and the oil specially known as whale oil, an
inferior article in commerce. Among the fishermen, he is indiscriminately
designated by all the following titles: the whale, the Greenland whale, the
black whale, the great whale, the true whale, the right whale. There is a deal
of obscurity concerning the identity of the species thus multitudinously baptized.
What then is the whale which I include in the second species of my folios? It
is the great mysticetus of the English naturalists, the Greenland whale of the
English whaleman, the bale ordinire of the French whaleman, the growins
wallfish of the Swedes. It is the whale which for more than two centuries past
has been hunted by the Dutch and English in the Arctic seas. It is the whale
which the American fishermen have long pursued in the Indian Ocean on the
Brazil banks in the northwest coast and in various other parts of the world
designated by them right whale cruising grounds. Some pretend to see a
difference between the Greenland whale of the English and the right whale of
the Americans, but they precisely agree in all their grand features. Nor has
there yet been presented a single determinate fact upon which to ground a
radical distinction. It is by endless subdivisions based upon the most
inconclusive differences that some departments of natural history become so
repellingly intricate. The right whale will elsewhere be treated of at some
length with reference to elucidating the sperm whale.
Book one, Folio. Chapter 3, Finnback.
Under this head, I reckon a monster which by the various names of Finnback,
Tallspout, and Long John, has been seen almost in every sea, and is commonly the
whale whose distant jet is so often described by passengers crossing the
Atlantic. in the New York packet tracks.
In the length he attains, and in his baine, the finback resembles the right
whale, but is of a less portly girth and a lighter color approaching to olive.
His great lips present a cable-like aspect, formed by the intertwisting,
slanting folds of large wrinkles. His grand distinguishing feature, the fin
from which he derives his name, is often a conspicuous object. This fin is some
three or four feet long, growing vertically from the hinder part of the
back of an angular shape and with a very sharp pointed end. Even if not the
slightest other part of the creature be visible, this isolated fin will at times
be seen plainly projecting from the surface. When the sea is moderately calm
and slightly marked with spherical ripples, and this gnomomenlike fin
stands up and cast shadows upon the wrinkled surface, it may well be
supposed that the watery circle surrounding it somewhat resembles a dial
with its style and wavy hourlines engraved on it. On that aaz dial, the
shadow often goes back. The finback is not gregarious. He seems a whale hater,
as some men are, manhaters, very shy, always going solitary,
unexpectedly rising to the surface in the remotest and most sullen waters. His
straight and single lofty jet rising like a tall misanthropic spear upon a
barren plane gifted with such wondrous power and velocity and swimming as to
defy all present pursuit from man. This leviathan seems the banished and
unconquerable cane of his race bearing for his mark that style upon his back.
from having the baine in his mouth. The finback is sometimes included with the
right whale among a theoretic species denominated whale bone whales, that is
whales with baine. Of these so-called whale bone whales, there would seem to
be several varieties, most of which, however, are little known. Broad-nosed
whales and beaked whales, pike headed whales, bunched whales, underjawed
whales and rostrated whales are the fisherman's names for a few sorts.
In connection with this appelative of whale bone whales, it is of great
importance to mention that however such a nomenclature may be convenient in
facilitating alusions to some kinds of whales, yet it is in vain to attempt a
clear classification of the leviathan founded upon either his baine or hump or
fin or teeth. Notwithstanding that those marked parts or features very obviously
seem better adapted to afford the basis for a regular system of cytology than
any other detached bodily distinctions which the whale in his kinds presents.
How then, the baine, hump, back, fin, and teeth, these are things whose
peculiarities are indiscriminately dispersed among all sorts of whales
without any regard to what may be the nature of their structure and other and
more essential particulars. Thus, the sperm whale and the humpback whale each
has a hump, but there the similitude ceases. Then this same humpback whale
and the Greenland whale, each of these has bene. But there again the similitude
ceases and it is just the same with the other parts above mentioned. In various
sorts of whales they form such irregular combinations or in the case of any one
of them detached such an irregular isolation as utterly to defy all general
methodization formed upon such a basis.
On this rock every one of the whale naturalists has split.
But it may possibly be conceived that in the internal parts of the whale, in his
anatomy, there at least we shall be able to hit the right classification.
Nay, what thing, for example, is there in the Greenland whale's anatomy more
striking than his bene? Yet we have seen that by his bellin it is impossible to
correctly classify the Greenland whale.
And if you descend into the bowels of the various Leviathans, why there you
will not find distinctions a 50th part as available to the systematizer as
those external ones already enumerated.
What then remains nothing but to take hold of the whales bodily in their
entire liberal volume and boldly sort them that way. And this is the
bibliographical system here adopted and it is the only one that can possibly
succeed for it alone is practicable.
To proceed book one folio chapter 4 humpback. This whale is often seen on
the northern American coast. He has been frequently captured there and towed into
harbor. He has a great pack on him like a peddler or you might call him the
elephant and castle whale.
At any rate, the popular name for him does not sufficiently distinguish him
since the sperm whale also has a hump, though a smaller one. His oil is not
very valuable. He has baileine. He is the most gamesome and light-hearted of
all whales, making more gay foam and white water generally than any other of them.
Book one, Folio. Chapter 5. Razerback.
Of this whale, little is known but his name. I have seen him at a distance off
Cape Horn. Of a retiring nature, he eludes both hunters and philosophers.
Though no coward, he has never yet shown any part of him but his back, which
rises in a long, sharp ridge. Let him go. I know little more of him, and nor
does anybody else. Book one. Folio.
Chapter 6. Sulfurbottom. Another retiring gentleman with a brimstone
belly, doubtless got by scraping along the Tartarian tiles in some of his
profounder divings. He is seldom seen, at least I have never seen him, except
in the remoter southern seas, and then always at too great a distance to study
his countenance. He is never chased. He would run away with rope walks of line.
Prodigies are told of him. Adue, sulfurbottom, I can say nothing more
that is true of ye, nor can the oldest Nantucketer.
Thus ends book one, Folio, and now begins book two, Octavo.
Octavos.
These embrace the whales of middling magnitude among which present may be
numbered one the grampus, two the blackfish, three the narwhale, four the
thrasher, five the killer.
Footnote. Why this book of whales is not denominated the quarto is very plain.
Because while the whales of this order, those smaller than those of the former
order, nevertheless retain a proportionate likeness to them in
figure, yet the bookbinder's quorto volume, in its dimensioned form, does
not preserve the shape of the folio volume, but the octavo volume does. End of footnote.
Book two, octavo, chapter 1, grandpas.
Though this fish, whose loud sonorous breathing, or rather blowing, has
furnished a proverb to landsmen, is so well known a denisin of the deep, yet he
is not popularly classed among whales.
But possessing all the grand distinctive features of the Leviathan, most
naturalists have recognized him for one.
He is of moderate octavo size, varying from 15 to 25 ft in length, and of
corresponding dimensions round the waist. He swims in herds. He is never
regularly hunted, though his oil is considerable in quantity and pretty good
for light. By some fisherman, his approach is regarded as premonatory of
the advance of the great sperm whale.
Book two, octavo, chapter 2, blackfish.
I give the popular fisherman's names for all these fish, for generally they are
best. Where any name happens to be vague or inexpressive, I shall say so and
suggest another. I do so now, touching the blackfish, socalled, because
blackness is the rule among almost all whales. So call him the hyena whale, if
you please. His boracity is well known, and from the circumstance that the inner
angles of his lips are curved upwards, he carries an everlasting mephilian grin
on his face. This whale averages some 16 or 18 feet in length. He is found in
almost all latitudes. He has a peculiar way of showing his dorsal hooked fin in
swimming, which looks something like a Roman nose. When not more profitably
employed, these sperm whale hunters sometimes capture the hyena whale to
keep up the supply of cheap oil for domestic employment, as some frugal
housekeepers, in the absence of company, and quite alone by themselves, burn
unsaavory tallow instead of odorous wax.
Though their blubber is very thin, some of these whales will yield you upwards
of 30 gallons of oil.
Book two, octavo, chapter 3, narwhale.
that is nostril whale. Another instance of a curiously named whale, so named, I
suppose, from his peculiar horn being originally mistaken for a peaked nose.
The creature is some 16 ft in length, while its horn averages 5 ft, though
some exceed 10 and even attain to 15 ft.
Strictly speaking, this horn is but a lengthened tusk growing out from the jaw
in a line a little depressed from the horizontal, but it is only found on the
sinister side, which has an ill effect, giving its owner something analogous to
the aspect of a clumsy left-handed man.
What precise purpose this ivory horn or lance answers, it would be hard to say.
It does not seem to be used like the blade of the swordfish and billfish,
though some sailors tell me that the narwhale employs it for a rake in
turning over the bottom of the sea for food. Charlie Coffan said it was used
for an ice piercer, for the narwhale, rising to the surface of the polar sea,
and finding it sheetated with ice thrusts his horn up and so breaks
through. But you cannot prove either of these surmises to be correct. My own
opinion is that however this one-sided horn may really be used by the narwhale,
however that may be, it would certainly be very convenient to him for a folder
in reading pamphlets. The narwhale I have heard called the tusked whale, the
horned whale, and the unicorn whale. He is certainly a curious example of the
unicornism to be found in almost every kingdom of animated nature. From certain
cloistered old authors, I have gathered that this same sea unicorn's horn was in
ancient days regarded as the great antidote against poison, and as such
preparations of it brought immense prices. It was also distilled to a
volatile salts for fainting ladies, the same way that the horns of the male deer
are manufactured into heartsorn.
Originally, it was in itself accounted an object of great curiosity. Black
letter tells me that Sir Martin Frobisher, on his return from that
voyage, when Queen Best did gallantly wave her jeweled hand to him from a
window of Greenwich Palace as his bold ship sailed down the tempames, quote,
"When Sir Martin returned from that voyage," Seth Blacklet Letter, on bended
knees, he presented to her highness a prodigious long horn of the Narwhale,
which for a long period after hung in the castle at Windsor. End quote. an
Irish author of hers that the Earl of Leester on bended knees did likewise
present to her highness another horn pertaining to a land beast of the unicorn nature.
The narwhale has a very picturesque leopardike look being of a milk white
ground color dotted with round and oblong spots of black. His oil is very
superior, clean and fine, but there is little of it and he is seldom hunted. He
is mostly found in these circumpolar seas.
Book two. Octavo. Chapter 4. Killer. Of this whale. Little is precisely known to
the Nantucketer, and nothing at all to the professed naturalist. From what I
have seen of him at a distance, I should say he was about the bigness of a
grampus. He is very savage, a sort of Fiji fish. He sometimes takes the great
folio whales by the lip and hangs there like a leech till the mighty brood is
worried to death. The killer is never hunted. I never heard what sort of oil
he has. Exception might be taken to the name bestowed upon this whale on the
ground of its indistinctness. For we are all killers on land and on sea,
bonaparts and sharks included.
Book two. Octavo. Chapter 5. Thrasher.
This gentleman is famous for his tail, which he uses for a feral in thrashing
his foes. He mounts the folio whales back, and as he swims, he works his
passage by flogging him, as some school masters get along in the world by a
similar process. Still less is known of the thrasher than of the killer. Both
are outlaws, even in the lawless seas.
Thus ends book two, Octavo, and begins book three, Duesimo.
duodesimos.
These include the smaller whales. One, the huzzah porpus. Two, the alggerine
porpus. Three, the mely mouth porpus. To those who have not chance specifically
to study the subject, it may possibly seem strange that fishes not commonly
exceeding four or 5 ft should be marshaled among whales, a word which in
the popular sense always conveys the idea of huggeeness. But the creatures
set down above as duodesimos are infallibly whales by the terms of my
definition of what a whale is, i.e. a spouting fish with a horizontal tail.
Book three, duodeimo chapter 1. Huzzah porpus. This is the common porpus found
almost all over the globe. The name is of my own bestowyl, for there are more
than one sort of porposes, and something must be done to distinguish them. I call
him thus because he always swims in hilarious schos which upon the broad sea
keep tossing themselves to heaven like caps in a Fourth of July crowd. Their
appearances generally hailed with delight by the mariner. Full of fine
spirits. They invariably come from the breezy billows to windward. They are the
lads that always live before the wind.
They are accounted a lucky omen. If you yourself can withstand three cheers at
beholding these vivacious fish, then heaven help you. The spirit of godly
gamesomeness is not in you. A well-fed, plump huzah porpus will yield you one
good gallon of good oil, but the fine and delicate fluid extracted from his
jaws is exceedingly valuable. It is in request among jewelers and watch makers.
Sailors put it on their hones. Porpus meat is good eating, you know. It may
never have occurred to you that a porpus spouts. Indeed, his spout is so small
that it is not very readily discernible, but the next time you have a chance,
watch him, and you will then see the great sperm whale himself in miniature.
Book three, Duodesimo. Chapter 2, Algerine Corpus, a pirate, very savage.
He is only found, I think, in the Pacific. He is somewhat larger than the
Huzah porpus, but much of the same general make. Provoke him and he will
buckle to a shark. I have lowered for him many times, but never yet saw him captured.
Book three, Duodesimo. Chapter 3.
Meymouth porpus. The largest kind of porpus, and only found in the Pacific,
so far as it is known. The only English name by which he has hitherto been
designated is that of the fissurers right whale porpus from the circumstance
that he is chiefly found in the vicinity of that folio. In shape he differs in
some degree from the huzah porpus being of a less rotund and jolly girth. Indeed
he is of quite a neat and gentlemanlike figure. He has no fins on his back most
other porpuses have. He has a lovely tail and sentimental Indian eyes of a
hazel hue, but his mely mouth spoils all. Though his entire back down to his
side fins, is of a deep sable, yet a boundary line distinct as the mark in a
ship's hull, called the bright waist, that line streaks him from stem to
stern, with two separate colors, black above and white below. The white
comprises part of his head and the whole of his mouth, which makes him look as if
he had just escaped from a felonious visit to a meal bag, a most mean and
mely aspect. His oil is much like that of the common porpus.
Beyond the duesimo, this system does not proceed in as much as the porpus is the
smallest of the whales. Above you have all the Leviathans of note, but there
are a rabble of uncertain, fugitive, half-fabulous whales, which as an
American whaleman I know by reputation, but not personally. I shall enumerate
them by their folks appellations, for possibly such a list may be valuable to
future investigators who may complete what I have here but begun. If any of
the following whales shall hereafter be caught and marked, then he can readily
be incorporated into this system according to his folio octavo or duode
decimo magnitude. The bottl-nose whale, the junk whale, the puddingheaded whale,
the cape whale, the leading whale, the cannon whale, the scrag whale, the
coppered whale, the elephant whale, the iceberg whale, the quag whale, the blue
whale, etc. From Icelandic, Dutch, and old English authorities, there might be
quoted other lists of uncertain whales blessed with all manner of uncouthed
names, but I omit them as altogether obsolete, and can hardly help suspecting
them for mere sounds full of Leviathanism, but signifying nothing.
Finally, it was stated at the outset that this system would not be here, and
at once perfected. You cannot but plainly see that I have kept my word.
But I now leave my cological system standing thus unfinished, even as the
great cathedral of Cologne was left with the crane still standing upon the top of
the uncompleted tower. For small erections may be finished by their first
architects. Grand ones, true ones, ever leave the copstone to posterity. God
keep me from ever completing anything.
This whole book is but a draft. Nay, but the draft of a draft. Oh, time,
strength, cash, and patience.